Abby Shute Merchant Papers, 1882-1982
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Abby Shute Merchant Papers
1912-1940
Merchant, Abby
MS 102
1 box (.5 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Playwright. Typescripts of plays, some with explanatory notes.
Biographical Note
Abby Shute Merchant was born on February 3rd, 1882 in Gloucester, Massachusetts, to Lewis H. and Hannah van P. Merchant. After graduating from Gloucester High School, she earned an A.B. from Smith College in 1904. She then worked as an editor, first at Munsey's Magazine, 1904-06, and for Craftsman in 1909. She then edited a variety of titles for Street and Smith Publishers, 1909-12. From 1913-15, she took "an advanced course in dramatic technique" with George Pierce Baker at Harvard where she met Mark W. Reed. In 1915 and 1916 she was director and co-owner with J.A. Crafton and Mark Reed of The Prairie Playhouse, in Galesburg, Illinois, one of the first attempts to take the "little theatre movement" to rural regional theatres to use repertory techniques in community setting. She returned to New York and worked as a playwright often working collaboratively with Mark Reed. Abby and her sister Helen (Smith class of 1899) retired to Tryon, North Carolina circa 1949.
Abby Shute Merchant died in Tryon, North Carolina on July 27th, 1982.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Abby Shute Merchant Papers consist of .5 linear ft. and consist of a small amount of biographical material plus typescripts of eight plays authored by Merchant, 1912-40.
The Papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
Abby Shute Merchant donated typescripts of seven of her plays to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1952. The eighth script came from Virginia Otis Locke in 2013.
Additional materials about Abby Merchant are available in the Smith College Archives
Search Terms
Merchant, Abby; Women dramatists, American--20th century--Biography--Sources; Drama--United States--History--20th century
- Biographical materials (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Scripts (Box 1)
  - "Burden of Beauty," 1932 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "The Dramatist" or "Mr. Pierrot Smith," 1928 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Irish Dew," 1920 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Land Ahead!" n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- "Love and Lucy: a play in three acts," 1927 (Box 6)
  - "Love Story," n.d. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - "The New Englander," 1912 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - "The Unbent Twig" or "Your Loving Son," 1940 (Box 6, Folder 9)